Hello everyone and welcome. This is Dr. Michael
Greger coming to you live from my treadmill,
which I am now turning off since we got so
many complaints last time. I try to role
model healthy behavior, but at the same
time don't want to make anybody seasick.
This is another CME‑approved webinar—continuing
medical education for doctors and other health
care professionals, as should all of our
webinars going forward. I'm proud to declare
I have no relevant financial relationships with
ineligible companies to disclose. That kind of
declaration statement is necessary given a long,
checkered past of big pharma secretly propping
up paid shills to push their products. So now
they just non‑secretly prop up paid shills who
push their products, but I'm not one of them. If
at any time you run into technical difficulties,
there are live chat room staff standing by. But
let me paste that link into the chat there for
everybody. If they're unable to help, we also
have NutritionFacts.org staff standing by,
too. And I will paste that into the chat box as
well. Please reserve the Q&A button that you see
in the Zoom window for content questions. Today's
webinar is only an hour, but I've reserved lots
of time for Q&A at the end; please feel free
to add your questions at any time by clicking
on the Q&A button. And the NutritionFacts team
will be compiling them to be answered at the
end. You don't have to worry about taking
notes or anything after the webinar is over.
We're not only going to send you a full recording
of it, but also a free link to download all the
vertical videos in high def so you can see all the
videos in their full‑definition resolution glory.
Okay, today I'm going to be talking about how
to prevent and treat age‑related hearing loss,
which is taken from my "Preserving Your Hearing"
chapter of my upcoming book, How Not to Age,
which will be available free at your local public
library. And all these videos will eventually make
it onto NutritionFacts.org for everyone to watch.
But you get to see them right here, right now,
starting with the good news that age‑related
hearing loss is not inevitable. Let's do it.
In the United States,
age-related hearing loss affects
about a quarter of those in their 60s,
more than half of those in their 70s,
and 80 percent of those in their 80s.
More than 95 percent of centenarians
have been found to have severe hearing loss.
Because of impaired communication,
this may lead to social isolation,
loneliness, and depression.
It may even threaten one’s life
due to an associated increase
in motor vehicle accidents.
What can we do to prevent
age-related hearing loss?
It’s said to be a natural part
of the aging process,
but that’s what we used to think
about pathological conditions
like high blood pressure.
The vast majority of people
eventually develop hypertension,
just like the vast majority of people
eventually lose their hearing;
so, it must just be an inevitable consequence
of growing old, right?
But then it was discovered
that there were rural populations
living in Africa and Asia
that ate and lived healthier,
that didn’t experience an inexorable rise
in blood pressure as they aged.
So, it appeared hypertension
was more a lifestyle choice
than an aging effect—and the same
may be true for hearing loss.
The Mabaan tribe living
in the Sudanese desert
was found to retain
their hearing into old age.
Other studies on isolated
native populations
found that exposure
to modern civilization
appeared to undercut
their hearing advantages.
What is it about our modern world
that appears to be leading
to a loss of hearing
as we grow older?
Age-related hearing loss
is a result of the premature death
of the sensory hair cells
in our inner ear
which turn vibrations
to electric signals to the brain.
Once they’re lost they don’t grow back;
so, prevention is critical.
The question is:
What's killing them?
A study of more than 2,000 twins
found that the heritability
of age-related hearing impairment
was only 25 percent;
so, most of risk
is due to nongenetic influences.
Risk factors include repeated exposure
to loud noises, smoking,
and ototoxic
(or hearing-damaging) medications.
Noise exposure early in life
appears to render the inner ear
more vulnerable to aging.
Animal studies suggest
exposure to low level
but constant noise over 60 decibels
may also be harmful.
This has not been demonstrated
in humans,
but if you use a white noise generator
to sleep
it can’t hurt to check
that it’s under 50.
Medications known to be ototoxic
include aminoglycoside antibiotics
(like streptomycin, amikacin,
neomycin, and kanamycin)
which are among the highest risk
medications for hair cell toxicity.
But NSAIDS, anti-inflammatory drugs
like aspirin, ibuprofen,
and naproxen, and loop diuretics
(for example furosemide sold as Lasix)
have also been linked
to progressive hearing loss.
However, the key to the preservation
of old-age-hearing
of the Mabaan tribe may be their diet.
The reason the Mabaan researchers
concluded that their diet
likely accounted for their lack
of age-related hearing loss
is because they also appeared
to lack something else:
coronary artery disease.
What kills more of us in the industrialized
world than anything else
doesn’t appear to touch them at all.
Their blood pressures
are also perfect their whole lives
at about 110 over 70 into their 70s
while we, on average, become hypertensive,
exceeding 130/80, starting in our 40s.
And no wonder—their diet
is “almost free of animal protein”
and centered around whole grains.
So, they suggested, in addition
to the absence of loud noise,
that atherosclerosis clogging
the small blood vessels
feeding their inner ears
may be the underlying cause
of age-related hearing loss
in most of the rest of the world.
But you don’t know
until...you put it to the test,
which I’ll cover next,
after dealing with a supplement
shown to slow
age-related hearing loss.
(Dr. Greger briefly summarizes the
video and introduces the next video)
Healthier diets are associated
with a significantly
lower risk of hearing loss,
and for all three diet quality scoring systems
these researchers used,
avoidance of meat was most strongly
associated with lower risk.
The Mabaan from my last video,
who preserved their hearing into old age,
ate little meat,
but also weren’t eating sugary junk,
explaining their almost total absence
of dental cavities.
A high glycemic diet of refined carbs
is also associated with developing
age-related hearing loss.
If it’s the blood sugar spikes,
that would explain why diabetics
and prediabetics
are also at higher risk.
Even among whole grains, sorghum,
which is the center of the Mabaan diet,
has a particularly low glycemic index
due to its resistant starch content,
causing about a 25 percent lower rise
in blood sugar compared to whole wheat.
Impaired blood circulation
may also explain how noise
damages the inner ear, as loud noises
cause constriction
of the accompanying blood vessels.
This may also help clarify the link
between obesity and hearing loss.
Excess weight may just be a proxy
for unhealthier diets,
but the pro-inflammatory state of obesity
can itself lead to vascular dysfunction.
Measures of systemic inflammation
seem to directly correlate
with age-related hearing loss,
as do measures of oxidative stress.
In my video on brain inflammation,
I introduced
the antioxidant defense activator Nrf2,
called “guardian of healthspan
and gatekeeper of species longevity.”
Those born with a genetic variant Nrf2
that doesn’t encode as well
are significantly more likely
to develop impaired hearing,
implicating the role of free radicals
in the process of hearing loss.
You can look in the back of people’s eyes
and measure the amount of macular pigment—
the lutein and zeaxanthin antioxidants
concentrated in greens—
and correlate that with superior hearing.
The population data on antioxidant intake
and hearing loss is mixed, though.
Take vitamin C for example.
Some studies show that higher vitamin C
intake is associated with better hearing,
but others failed to find
any significant connection.
The only way to tell
if antioxidants help or not—
you know the drill—
is to put them to the test.
Adding antioxidants to the diets of rats
seems to help prevent
age-related rat hearing loss,
but doing the same thing
in mice doesn’t appear to help.
The most exciting preclinical data
may be a study
in which aged rats randomized
to added blueberries
looked like they had a reversal
in hearing deficits,
in fact ending up better
than the young rats.
Wait, I thought hair cells
don’t regenerate?
Our ability to hear doesn’t just have to do
with our ears, but our brain.
As we age, our auditory cortex
in the temporal lobe of our brain
loses some of its ability to discriminate
and understand speech
even in a quiet environment.
We don’t just need to sense sounds,
but make sense out of them.
That’s where blueberries
seemed to come in,
reversing the age-related cognitive deficits
in auditory processing.
But what about in people?
There are studies lacking control groups that
documented improvements in hearing loss,
giving people antioxidant supplements
like vitamins A, E, C, and alpha-lipoic acid.
But when properly put to the test
in a randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial of a whole list
of antioxidants, the supplements flopped—
no effect on any of the
measured hearing aspects.
Is there any supplement that has been shown
to help with hearing in older adults?
Yes, folic acid,
the supplement form of folate,
found concentrated
in beans and greens.
Some observational studies
had found that higher levels of folate
in the blood seem
to correlate with better hearing,
but maybe that’s just a marker
of eating a healthier diet in general.
So, Dutch researchers set out
on an ambitious three-year double-blind
placebo-controlled trial randomizing
more than 700 older men and women
to take 800 μg of folic acid a day
or an indistinguishable placebo.
Excitingly, those who had been taking
the folic acid
suffered significantly less decline
in hearing at speech frequencies.
The effect size was rather small,
such that one might expect
the proportion of men, for example,
who would be hearing aid candidates
at age 75 might drop
from 33 percent to 22 percent
with folic acid supplementation.
Also note the study was done
in the Netherlands, where, at the time,
the food supply was not fortified
with folic acid.
In the U.S.,
where folic acid fortification
has been mandated
in refined grain products for decades,
it’s unclear how much additional benefit
supplements might add.
Regardless, the healthiest sources are dark
green leafy vegetables and legumes.
(A cup of cooked lentils has 90 percent
of adult daily needs.)
(Dr. Greger briefly summarizes the
video and introduces the next video)
A 2021 scoping review on the role
of nutrition in the development
and prevention of age-related hearing loss
screened thousands of papers
and concluded that “Diets rich
in saturated fats and cholesterol
have deleterious effects on hearing
that could be prevented by lower consumption.”
The case of the Mabaan I noted
before makes for a compelling story,
but on what exactly
are they basing their conclusion?
It’s true that in laboratory animals
you can prove it.
Randomize rats to added saturated fat
or chinchillas to added dietary cholesterol,
and scientists can show
atherosclerosis-inducing diets
exacerbate inner ear damage
and hearing loss,
even without noise exposure.
But that doesn’t necessarily mean
the same is true in people.
There is cogent epidemiological data.
For example, a study of thousands of twins
was able to draw a significant link
between a high cholesterol diet
and hearing impairment.
In the Blue Mountains Hearing Study,
which enrolled thousands of older men
and women to study
age-related hearing loss,
dietary cholesterol was the nutrient
component
most associated with hearing loss.
Those eating about two eggs worth of
cholesterol a day
had 34 percent greater odds
of hearing loss
compared to those only getting
about a single egg’s worth.
Consistent with a vascular cause,
those on statins,
and particularly those at higher doses,
appeared to be at lower risk.
The researchers suggest
that high cholesterol intake
may interfere with the circulation
within the inner ear itself,
or atherosclerotic inflammatory changes
could reduce blood flow
to the tiny arteries feeding the inner ear.
But how about looking inside the arteries
to see if this is actually true?
The extent and severity
of coronary artery disease in the heart,
as determined by angiogram, was found
to closely correlate to hearing loss.
Since atherosclerosis is a systemic disease
affecting the entire arterial tree,
this has relevance for the arteries
feeding the inner ear.
The same was found for the amount
of atherosclerotic plaque
found in the carotid arteries in the neck.
The greater the plaque, the poorer the
hearing, and the more plaque they found,
the greater risk of further
hearing impairment
measured over
the subsequent five years.
Getting closer, but how about the arteries
that directly supply the inner ear?
Early autopsy data suggested sclerotic
changes in the blood vessels of older ears
contribute to inner ear degeneration,
and these days,
direct imaging studies correlate
the degree of hearing loss
with atherosclerotic narrowing
of those inner ear arteries.
Now all we need is an interventional trial
to wrap it all up in a bow.
Yes, high-cholesterol
and high saturated fat diets
have been shown to kill off
those critical inner ear cells
and cause hearing loss in lab animals,
but it’s not like you can lock
hundreds of people up for a few years
and force them to eat
different amounts of saturated fat
and see what happens to their hearing.
Oh, but you can, and they did:
The Finnish Mental Hospital Study.
In 1960, one of two mental hospitals
near Helsinki had their menus changed
to decrease their intake
of saturated animal fat.
Then, after a few years, the two hospitals
switched their menus over.
It was one of the first
interventional trials of its kind
suggesting that you could decrease
heart disease deaths
by decreasing saturated fat intake.
Ah, but what happened to their hearing?
It followed the exact same pattern.
As their heart disease got worse,
so did their hearing.
And then when the hospitals switched,
the reverse happened.
And not just by a little.
Those in their 50s
in the lower saturated fat hospital
ended up with significantly better hearing
than the group in the control hospital
that was ten years younger.
The researchers concluded: "our
audiological studies lead us to conclude
that diet is an important factor
in the prevention of hearing loss.”
(Dr. Greger responds to questions
for the remainder of the video)